Today's דף daf is מ"א, mem-aleph, and we are in the middle
of talking about the red string. And today,
oh, thank you so much, is this from you? Thank you, wonderful.
And, and, and,
and while today's דף daf is really not going to deal with
the עבודה, avodah, we're really going to be focusing on the red
string and other things that are related with the red string. I
always feel it's important to periodically just review where we're up to
in the עבודה. avodah. And now we've got some nice markers, right?
So here we are going to do step number one, which is
his פר, par, right, which is in the צפון tzafon here. Whoops,
I know I got shadows. Let's get this right. The head
is
faced this way, the body is this way, כהן גדול Kohen Gadol
stands here, does וידוי. vidui. That's step number one, okay? וידוי פרו,
vidui paro,
okay?
Step number two, walks over here, here are the two goats. I
pointed
that out, okay,
and he does the גורלות. goralot. He
does the גורלות goralot first thing, you can get the idea.
Okay, anyway, I don't know what that is.
Okay, that's been done
over there, I don't know. That's step number two. I don't know,
according to the earlier גמרא, Gemara, maybe it's צפון, tzafon, okay, but
you wanted this because you didn't want him running around but it's
not clear. Anyway, you have the גורלות. goralot. Okay, you have him
do the selecting, selecting of the גורל. goral. Then step number three
is, right,
he's still over here and he does the red string.
He does it or someone else?
Well, that's a good question. I mean the language is קשר, kashar,
I think. Yeah, קשר. kashar. Could be, could be whoever, but I
doubt, I doubt he has to do it, there's no discussion.
Is there hint in the תורה Torah about the red string?
No, the red string is not in תורה Torah anywhere. There's a
red string in the תורה Torah by other things, by the פרה
אדומה, Parah Adumah, whatever. Exactly born, exactly, yeah, but not for this.
You know, for us it's... I know, but for there is that,
you know, for I
was just asking, it's very... I know, it's a very symbolic thing,
but it's not, it's not in the תורה. Torah. Is there any,
okay? So anyway, okay, so he does the red string, he does
the red string. Now, according to the גמרא, Gemara, right, according to
the משנה, Mishnah, he puts the red string,
oh, we could use red for that,
he puts the red string on the one לעזאזל, La'azazel, and then
the one לעזאזל La'azazel gets put where by the, gets sent to
where it's going out, okay, we'll discuss where that is, but that
gets put to, you know, by the gate where it's going to
go from, where it's going to leave, head out, it goes to
the gate out. And then there was an ambiguous line in the
משנה Mishnah and he, and it sounded like the simple reading is
he takes the one that's להשם L'hashem and he just gets it
ready to be שחט, shechted, puts it wherever it's going to be
שחט. shechted. But the גמרא, Gemara, and this does not as far
as I know is not echoed in any of the like liturgy,
in any of the other recappings of the עבודה, avodah, but at
least according to the גמרא, Gemara, he puts a red string around
the neck of the one that's going to be שחט. shechted. Okay,
so that was step number three was the red string. And then
he walks back here and we get to step number four, which
is וידוי פר vidui par number two, פרו paro number two, and
this is for all of the כהנים. Kohanim. Okay, that's where we
are in terms of the משנה. Mishnah. Now we have been talking
about the red string, so in addition to saying that it went
around the neck of the one that was to be שחט, shechted,
we are comparing it to other red strings, ones that are actually
in the תורה, Torah, and the first comparison was to the red
string of the פרה אדומה. Parah Adumah. And the גמרא Gemara has
a discussion, one of them has a minimum, the other does not
have a minimum. The reason for having a minimum for this is
because you need to then cut the string in two later, part
remains between the horns and the other part that you keep while
the animal goes over the cliff so you can see if it
turns white. So that's a minimum length. But the red string that
actually is in the תורה Torah together with the אזוב ezov and
the עץ ארז, eitz erez, the hyssop and the cedar, they get
put into the burning of the פרה אדומה, Parah Adumah, there it
needs a minimum because not of length but of weight, because it
says והשליך, v'hishlich, you cast it. So you know, it has to
sort of, when you cast something in, it has to fall down,
you know, sort of like in an immediate way, not float down.
You wouldn't say you cast it in if it then sort of
like floated down like this. So that's the issue whether that's really
true. Does it have to be a minimum weight to ensure that
it sort of like drops immediately when you throw it in? So
there's that debate about כובד koved and we'll pick up with that.
So the גמרא, Gemara, let's take a look now, מ"א עמוד ב'
mem-aleph amud bet on the bottom.
It says like this, אמר ליה רבא, amar lei Rava, I'll just
read that five lines from the bottom where the lines are wide,
אמר ליה רבא, amar lei Rava, so רבא Rava said, כובד תנאי
היא. koved tana'i hi. There's actually a debate whether there needs to
be a certain weight in the string for the פרה אדומה Parah
Adumah to make sure that it does not float down but that
it goes down quickly. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara says like this,
ודפרה לא בעי חלוקה. u'd'parah lo ba'i chalukah. and and the פרה
אדומה Parah adumah *Parah Adumah* does not need to be split, it
only needs the weight, okay, whereas the פר par *Par* for the
שעיר Sa'ir *Seir* needs to be split by the פרה אדומה Parah
adumah. *Parah Adumah*, the only issue is is the what do you
call it? Is the oh, I'm sorry, that's actually a question. פרה
Parah, לא בעי חלוקה *Parah lo ba'ei chalukah*, is that true that
the פרה אדומה parah adumah, *Parah Adumah* does not need to be
split? איתיביה אביי *Eitiveih Abaye*, so אביי *Abaye* asked on this. כיצד
הוא עושה *Keitzad hu oseh*? Okay, 'cause we said that the one
for the goat had to be split, but the פרה אדומה parah
adumah, *Parah Adumah* we're saying is only about the weight. Is that
really true? But אביי *Abaye* asks, כיצד הוא עושה *Keitzad hu oseh*?
What would he do? This is by a משנה *Mishnah* by פרה
אדומה parah adumah *Parah Adumah*. כורכן בשירי לשון *Korchan beshiyarei lashon*, you
wrap the ארז *Erez* and the אזוב *Ezov* with the red string,
but the language here is with the remnant of the red string.
So that seems to indicate that even the red string for פרה
אדומה parah adumah *Parah Adumah* had to be cut into two, and
therefore would need some minimum. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, אימא
בזנב לשון *Eima biznav lashon*. No, it doesn't mean a remnant as
if you cut it in two, it means like a frayed part
of it. Like you know רש"י Rashi's *Rashi* sort of speaks about
like, you know, you fray something at the bottom, like a comb,
and it's like you know, sort of its frayed at the bottom.
So that's the way of saying שירי *Shiyarei*, remnant, not literally remnant,
but it looks like a remnant because it's like a frayed-
Why does he tie with a regular-?
Yeah, I don't know. Okay. אמר רבי חנין אמר רב Rav *Amar
Rabbi Chanin amar Rav*, עץ ארז ואזוב ושני תולעת etz erez ve-ezov
u-shni tola'at. שקלטתן שלהבת כשרה *Etz erez v'ezov v'shani tola'at shekaltatan shalhevet
kesherah*. Now, when you let's say you threw it into the into
the conflagration here, but they were not actually they didn't actually fall
in, you know, they were in they were over the fire, and
they got burnt over the fire. Okay, so I threw my red
string in, I threw my hyssop in, but rather than falling into
the fire, when it was over the fire, it already got burnt
by the fire. Is that good? Is that, you know, or does
that make it and is it now a good in terms of
the ashes of the פרה אדומה parah adumah *Parah Adumah*, did I
do the ritual correctly?
So it was so so he says,
שקלטתן שלהבת *Shekaltatan shalhevet*, if the flame burned them, כשרה *Kesherah*, even
without falling into the fire, it's כשרה *Kesherah*. מיתיבי *Meitivei*, the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says I'll ask you on this, we have a ברייתא
beraisa. *Braita* that says נשלהב הלשון *Nishavhev halashon*, if the string gets
charred, מביא לשון אחר ומקדש *Meivi lashon acher u'mekadesh*, you need to
bring another string and sanctify, because the whole process of making the
ashes of the פרה אדומה parah adumah *Parah Adumah* is called קידוש
kidush *Kiddush*. So מקדש Mikdash, *Mekadesh* means by bringing the other string
and throwing it in, that will be part of the, you know,
making of the ashes of the פרה אדומה parah adumah *Parah Adumah*.
So you the string being charred is not enough, it has to
fall into the fire. So אמר אביי לא קשיא *Amar Abaye lo
kashya*, it's not difficult. כאן דקולחא כאן דמכסכסא *Kan dekolchas, kan demichsefes*.
What type of a fire is it? Is it a fire that
has like, you know, rising flames or is it a low fire?
If it's a fire that has very high flames, and so it's
very high over the fire and it gets charred that way, you're
not יוצא *Yotzei*, 'cause the language in the תורה Torah, *Torah* is
אל תוך שרפת הפרה *El toch srefat haparah*, into the very burning,
into the conflagration. But if it has low flames, right, and it's
and it gets burnt, and so that means it's very close to
actually the wood or whatever, or the, you know, the actual source
of the root of the flame, so that's considered אל תוך *El
toch*. So the point here is, being burnt by the fire is
not enough, it has to be אל תוך *El toch*. So if
it's high up and is burnt by the fire, that's not enough,
but if it's low down, it doesn't actually have to fall and
hit the ground, doesn't have to actually fall and hit the, you
know, and hit the physical stuff on the bottom, but it has
to be near the bottom to be considered it's in the midst
of the conflagration. All right, so that's where we are with that.
Now back to the issue about the string and its is there
a minimum
amount? רבא Rava אמר
*Rava omer* כובד Koved, תנאי *Koved tano'i*. Now רבא *Rava* said before
that the issue of a minimum weight was for the פרה אדומה
parah adumah *Parah Adumah* for the string was a debate of תנאים
*Tanna'im*. דתניא *Detanya*, we talk in a ברייתא beraisa *Braita*, למה כורכן
*Lama korchan*? Why does
why does he wrap the the other two things, the hyssop and
the cedar, with the string? כדי שיהיו באגודה אחת *Kedei sheyihiyu ba'agudah
achat*. In order because it says, you know, they should all be
a bunch. So it's it's it says you should take them, so
take them as a unit. Okay, that's דברי רבי *Divrei Rabbi*. That's
what רבי *Rabbi* says. רבי אלעזר Elazar ברבי שמעון אומר *Rabbi Elazar
b'Rabbi Shimon omer* כדי שיהיה בהן כובד Koved, *Kedei sheyisbahein koved*. No,
there's not a sort of a conceptual idea of do it as
a unit, but you but there's an idea of a practical issue
of they have to fall into the fire. So if you wrap
them all together, then they have density and weight and all of
them will fall into the fire rather than float in.
Well the wood is never going to float in anyway because it's
wood.
Right, okay, so but that helps the other things. So there so
what you see is according to רבי אלעזר Elazar. ברבי שמעון *Rabbi
Elazar b'Rabbi Shimon*, there's an importance that they have some real weight
to them. Okay, ויפלו לתוך שרפת הפרה *V'yipelu letoch srefat haparah*. And
they will fall like more directly into the fire. כי אתא רב
Rav דימי אמר רבי יוחנן *Ki ata Rav Dimi amar Rabbi Yochanan*.
Now, when רב Rav's דימי *Rav Dimi* came from ארץ ישראל Eretz
Yisrael, *Eretz Yisrael*, he said in the name of רבי יוחנן *Rabbi
Yochanan*, שלש לשונות שמעתי *Shalosh leshonot shamati*. I heard about three, you
know, strands of red. That's all so funny because you know, as
I said, you say שלש לשונות *Shalosh leshonot*, like I heard three
versions, right? But no, I heard about three, meaning about a teaching
about the three different red strings. אחת של פרה Parah *Achat shel
parah*, one of the פרה אדומה parah adumah *Parah Adumah*, which is
in the תורה Torah, *Torah*, we've been talking about.
the one of the goat that's sent away, which is, notice that
again we're completely ignoring the red string for the goat that's going
to be להשם, okay, the one that's on the goat that's going
to be sent away, which is not in the תורה, Torah but
is a very important part of the ritual, at least for us.
ואחת של מצורע, Va'achas shel metzora, and one of the מצורע, Metzora,
because by the מצורע Metzora as well it talks about taking a,
you know, a red string and a hyssop and using that in
the process of purifying the מצורע. Metzora. So, and now what is
their difference in terms of minimums? אחת משקל עשרה זוז, Achas mishkal
asara zuz, one has to weigh ten זוז, Zuz, which is a
lot. ואחת משקל שני סלעים, Va'achas mishkal shnei sela'im, one only has
to weigh two סלעים, Sela'im, which is less. ואחת משקל שקל, Va'achas
mishkal shekel, and one only has to weigh a שקל. Shekel. So
again, it's different types of coins, זוז, Zuz, סלע, Sela, and שקל,
Shekel, so but it's easy to remember cause the numbers ten, two,
and one are also is the range of, it's you know, is
the in order of the different weights. Okay. ואין לי לפרש, V'ein
li lefaresh, and I can't explain which is which, meaning I don't
have a good explanation which you know has to be the weightiest,
which it's okay to be lighter, I can't figure it out. כי
אתא רבין, Ki ata Ravin, now when רבין Ravin came from
ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael. פירשה משמיה דרב יונתן, Pirshah mishmei deRav Yonatan,
so he now had an explanation in the name of רב יונתן.
Rav Yonatan. Maybe רב יונתן Rav Yonatan heard this from רב יוחנן
Rav Yochanan in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael So now we have another
visitor from ארץ ישראל Yisrael and he's going to explain this earlier
teaching. Top of מב עמוד א. Mem beis amud aleph. של פרה
משקל עשרה זוז, Shel parah mishkal asara zuz, the פרה אדומה parah
adumah, has to be the weightiest, ten זוז Zuz for the reason
we saw, because it has to be, because you have to throw
it in and it has to fall in. You know? So again,
maybe he felt that it was not in a bunch with the
wood, so it has to fall in on its own.
It's not in
a bunch, you didn't tie a string around it, or maybe it
has to, even if it is in a bunch, maybe you have
to have independently the ability to fall in by itself. Okay? So
that has to be the weightiest. ושעיר המשתלח משקל שני סלעים, Vesha'ir
hamishtaleach mishkal shnei sela'im, the one of the goat has to be
two סלעים, Sela'im, that's the medium amount. Why? Because that has to
be enough in order to cut it into two. Now of course
the funny thing is, is that has nothing to do with weight,
like weight is an indirect way assuming that we're talking about a
pretty a standard type of a you know, how thick is the
cloth?
Assuming you're talking about, or how thick is the string? You know,
assuming you're talking about a standard width, a standard string, then weight
will be an indirect way of determining length. But it is pretty
funny. Okay. But the שעיר Sa'ir, is the middle amount because the
issue there is about it being long enough for to, you know,
to divide into two. ושל מצורע משקל שקל, Veshel metzora mishkal shekel,
and the מצורע Metzora is only, it can only be a שקל
Shekel cause you don't need the idea of throwing it in and
you don't need to divide it into two. So of course I
don't know why you need any minimum. Where do they get this
idea of a שקל Shekel from? I have no idea. אמר רב
יוחנן, Amar Rav Yochanan, said רב יוחנן, Rav Yochanan, פליגי בה רבי
שמעון בן חלפתא ורבנן. Pligi bah Rabbi Shimon ben Chalafta v'rabanan. This
is a debate about רבי שמעון בן חלפתא Rabbi Shimon ben Chalafta
and the רבנן Rabanan about like which is more, which is less.
Okay, בפרה, B'parah, regarding the פרה אדומה. parah adumah חד אמר משקל
עשרה, Chad amar mishkal asara, one says like we said, it has
to be the weightiest in order to fall right into the fire.
וחד אמר משקל שקל. V'chad amar mishkal shekel. No, there's no idea
of כובד, Koved, like we said before, there's no idea of כובד,
and if there's no idea of כובד, it can even be as
light as possible. Okay, now why exactly it could be even lighter
than the מצורע Metzora is not clear.
Cause you have the wood,
it's heavy and it's going to fall. Maybe, but why can't the
מצורע Metzora be light?
Are we talking about quantity of thread that has the equivalent weight
of that coin?
Yes, yes. Not how much it costs?
No, no, no.
But if you had to put it in a balance and you
had the coin as a counterweight? No, no, no, no. We're talking
we're using coins to as a way of saying how much it
weighs, counterweight. Okay? So he says, you said that that the ten,
two, and one was פרה, Parah שעיר, and then the מצורע. Metzora.
He says, actually there's a debate. Some say the פרה Parah is
the heaviest in that ten, two, and one, the פרה Parah is
in the ten slot. But there's another opinion that the פרה Parah
is in the one slot, it's the lightest. Again, why it would
be lighter than מצורע Metzora I don't know, but if there's no
need for a particular weight for the string, the פרה Parah is
the lightest. String is very light. I know.
That's why I asked the question. It would be a large quantity
of thread.
But no, you could also think about, but you could also think
about like a cord, like you could think about rope. If the
word was rope instead of string, but you're right.
That might look more like a rope. And they had a dyed
string.
Yeah,
yeah, cause it had to be, it's not, no,
it's dyed, it's dyed red.
Ross
says the dye is from a non-kosher insect.
That, well, that's another conversation. וסימנא, Vesimana, now the way to remember
that the debate about the פרה Parah? is to the extremes, one
says ten and one says one, nobody says פרה parah, is the
middle position of two.
אחד המרבה ואחד הממעיט, Echad hamarbeh v'echad hamamit,
whether you do a lot or you do a little, ובלבד שיכוין
לבו לשמים, Uvilvad sheyachaven libo laShamayim,
a famous statement of חז"ל. Chazal. So it's saying one goes to
the one extreme, the other goes to the other extreme and nobody
takes the middle amount. You know it's the פרה? para Yeah, you
don't. Okay. אמר ליה רב ירמיה מדיפתי לרבינא, Amar lei Rav Yirmiyah
miDipti leRavina, so רב ירמיה Rav Yirmiyah from דיפתי Dipti of
דיפתי Dipti said to רבינא, Ravina, לא בפרה פליגי, Lo b'parah pligi,
which is now exactly what Michael said. So now you know there's
a debate of ten or one, the biggest or the least. But
he says, I don't. I don't think that the debate was about
the פרה אדומה para adumah, *Parah Adumah*, אלא בשיעורי המשתלח פליגי *Ela
bisi'arei hamishto'ale'ach pligi*. Okay, they debated the שיעורי המשתלח *si'arei hamishto'ale'ach*. Now
again, why would somebody say it had to be very heavy, whilst
the other person say very light? Again, no real explanation where those,
you know, where those positions are coming from.
Okay, you understand blowing off—was this tied around the horn?
Maybe, oh, maybe so it doesn't blow off, maybe so it doesn't
break, maybe that's a possibility. Well, let me just read it. והוא
יומא נח נפשיה דרב יא בר קיסי *Ve-hahu yoma nach nafshei de-Rav
Ya bar Kisi*. That day that they were, that they had the
debate about ten or one, whether they were debating the פרה parah.
*parah* or the שעיר *sa'ir*, but they were debating these various weights
of the string, was the day that רב Rav יא בר קיסי
*Rav Ya bar Kisi* passed away. ואנחו בה סימנא *Ve-anchu bah simana*,
as they placed a סימן *siman* on this, you know, to remember,
you know, to remember what the debate was about and to connect
it to the passing of this צדיק *tzadik* or this rabbi, רב
Rav יא בר קיסי מכפר כשעיר המשתלח *Rav Ya bar Kisi mechaper
ke-sa'ir hamishto'ale'ach*. רב Rav... יא בר קיסי *Rav Ya bar Kisi* atones
like the שעיר המשתלח *sa'ir hamishto'ale'ach* like atones. Now this actually is
a really fascinating line, meaning in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, you know,
it's just like, just like a mnemonic like אחד אמר מר ואחד
אמר מית *echad amar mar ve-echad amar mit*. So the way you
remember that they were debating about the goat, rather than that they
were debating about the פרה אדומה para adumah *Parah Adumah* is because
they were debating on the day he died, and the same way
the goat atones, מיתת צדיקים מכפרת mitat tzadikim mechaperet. *mitat tzadikim mechaperet*,
and so you can remember they were debating the goat. Okay, so
according to the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* it's just like a simple memory
tool. But obviously, it presents us with like a very serious theological
issue right here in the middle of discussing like different forms of
atonement. And something that I think that we're not always prepared to
acknowledge is that the idea, because of, you know, it has, because
then the Christians, you know, picked up on this and made it
central to their theology. But the idea that the, that the death
of a righteous person can bring about atonement. You know, so obviously
the Christian theology is all about, all about Jesus's death. But you
know, and the idea that somewhat of a comparison to that as
a type of a קרבן korban, *korban*. And so to see, so
the, you know, there's more, it is true that you can explain
it in, you know, more, I would say, I guess, practical terms.
When a righteous person dies, it causes everybody to reflect, it causes
a, you know, it leads to a process of תשובה *teshuvah*. But
it seems to be more than that, why
שעיר המשתלח *sa'ir hamishto'ale'ach*?
Right? It's—but it seems more than that, right? Something is cast away
from the community, right? It's not put on an altar up to
God, but somehow the fact of that we, you know, that loss
and that, you know, and that, well, I don't, you know, is,
you know, is the loss of that life from us brings about
some type—brings about some atonement. And it is interesting that it's also
a tone that we have a very hard time relating to the
שעיר המשתלח *sa'ir hamishto'ale'ach*, right? I mean, we love the ritual, we
love the idea that we're atoned for on יום כיפור Yom Kippur,
*Yom Kippur* and the red string and all of that. I mean,
some people it bothers them that the goat is broken into pieces.
Okay, but even bracketing that, but a theologically, right? I think we
can understand קרבנות korbanot, *korbanot*, you know, again, whether aesthetically we can,
you know, but we can understand it, you know? You bring something,
you know, that represents life, that represents something, you know, of your,
of your own effort, but it also represents life. You put it
on the altar, the smoke rises up to God, it's like the
giving of a life to God. We understand the power of the
ritual of קרבנות *korbanot*. But the שעיר לעזאזל se'ir la-azazel. *sa'ir la-azazel*
is like very strange, right? Why is that causing atonement? I mean,
it is that sense of throwing it away, scapegoat, blame it on
somebody else, and who's the עזאזל *Azazel*? Demon? What's the עזאזל *Azazel*?
So again, we'll talk about that more later. But it is—I just
want to point out that it's fascinating that these two ideas, which
I think we don't tend to talk about so much theologically, are
here being linked, that the שעיר לעזאזל *sa'ir la-azazel*, you know, brings
about atonement and the death of a צדיק *tzadik* brings about atonement.
And thinking about that as some type of a symbolic, something of,
you know, also ironic. The שעיר *sa'ir* has all the sins, the
צדיק *tzadik* presumably has all the merit, you know, but somehow both
of their deaths, you know, somehow, somehow brings about some metaphysical atonement.
So what do you want to say?
I wanted to mention two things. One, I mean, just quickly, I
just think that's way too rational an explanation for קרבנות *korbanot*. I
think they're all vicarious. In other words, instead of me on the
altar, it's the animal on the altar. And it's like the עקידה
*akeidah*, the paradigm. That's what the Christians like that also.
Well, okay, I—I—okay, I was—a long conversation there which—well, I was alluding,
I agree with that. I was alluding to that with the idea
of representing life. But yes, it's also part of that life could
be representing your life. I completely agree with that.
So, but I just want to ask again on language. Is the
word חוט *chut* as in חוט השני *chut ha-shani* the biblical word?
Yes, but I think לשון *lashon* as in לשון חכמים *leshon
chakhamim* is called a לשון
*lashon*. Yes, but I think לשון *lashon* generically is thread, but I
also think very often
in לשון חכמים *leshon chakhamim* it's,
right, it specifically means the thread, the red string.
Right, as opposed to a... wrought piece of cloth or a swath.
Yes, yes, yes. So a לשון is a thread, a string, correct.
Did you take the bolt though?
Right. Yeah, I think before I said cloth, I didn't mean that,
it's a string.
Because על המציאות, al hamitziut, it does something else, it's like the
way they translate that usually, לשון של זהורית leshon shel zehorit is
like bolt, bolts. That's the way I've seen it.
Maybe, maybe, but I think in most cases it means it means
a string. Yeah. Oh, okay. Wait.
What?
Oh, I would imagine it as a
as a piece of
cloth. Yeah, no, okay. All right. So,
I mean right, the Torah doesn't say what the what the material
is. The Torah says עץ ארז ואזוב ושני תולעת. tola'at Right, שני,
shni, you know,
is
is color.
Yeah, the color and תולעת is of the worm. That that's what
Charlie was saying, you know. So it doesn't tell you what is
dyed red. Right. But yes, yes.
So does the Gemara have this elsewhere and then compare to something
else or they just always compare to everything from the Mishnah?
No, often the Gemara just says it by itself, מיתת צדיקים מכפרת.
Okay.
All right, so now let's take a look. It says okay,
a דבר davar I thought you'd want to explain to me שעיר
לעזאזל. All right, anyway.
Anyway, so the Gemara says like this:
אמר רבי יצחק, amar Rabbi Yitzchak, שתי שחיטות שמעתי. shtei shechitot shamati.
Now we get back to עבודת יום כיפור. avodat Yom Kippur. We
were talking about three strings, now we're talking about two שחיטות. shechitot.
אחת של פרה ואחת של פר. achat shel parah ve-achat shel par.
One of the פרה, parah the פרה אדומה, para adumah and one
of his פר par on יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, the one we've
been talking about that he does the וידוי vidui on. And here
is the same we were talking about the different weights of strings,
we're going to talk about different הלכה halacha contrast and there were
debates about which weight to assign to which. We're going to talk
about a difference between the שחיטה shechitah of his פר par and
the פרה אדומה, para adumah, but there's going to be a debate
which is which. אחת כשרה בזר, achat kesherah be-zar, one of these,
either the פרה אדומה para adumah or אהרן Aharon's פר par of
יום כיפור, Yom Kippur. can be shechted by a non-כהן. kohen. ואחת
פסולה בזר, ve-achat psulah be-zar, and one cannot be shechted by a
non-כהן. kohen. ולא ידענא הי מינייהו, ve-lo yadana hei mineihu, I don't
know which is which. So, so what?
How can you not know?
Right, what's which one is obvious to you, Charlie?
Obviously something that's done in the עזרה azarah would be the one...
Well first of all, ישראל is מותר mutar into the עזרה azarah
when he needs to go in. Okay.
Right, but as specifically the כהן גדול kohen gadol on יום כיפור.
Yom Kippur?
Ah, so even though normally שחיטה כשרה בזר, shechitah kesherah be-zar, doesn't
everything have to be done by the כהן גדול kohen gadol on
יום כיפור? Yom Kippur But we just discussed, excuse me, we just
discussed something that might not have to be done by the כהן
גדול. kohen gadol. Which what was might not have to be done?
Right. Well that, but also drawing of the lots, that wasn't clear.
But drawing of the lots, right, that might be by the סגן
segan or might be by the left hand. So there are things
that are done on יום כיפור Yom Kippur? that are not considered
to be an עבודה avodah that might not require a כהן גדול.
kohen gadol. And that becomes the question of שחיטה, shechitah, which is
normally כשר בזר, kasher be-zar, right, does it require a כהן גדול
kohen gadol on יום כיפור? Yom Kippur, How much is it... All
right, all right, let's how much is it an עבודה avodah and
for this purpose. So let's take a look. ולא ידענא הי מינייהו.
ve-lo yadana hei mineihu. So איתמר, itmar, now we're going to figure
it out. שחיטת פרה ופר, shechitat parah u-par,
the פרה אדומה para adumah and the פר par of the כהן
גדול. kohen gadol. רב ושמואל, Rav u-Shmuel, debate of רב Rav, and
שמואל. Shmuel. חד אמר פרה פסולה chad amar parah psulah and means
with a by a זר. zar. One says the פרה אדומה Para
Aduma. is פסול pasul by a זר, zar, ופרו כשרה, u-paro kesherah,
and the cow of כהן גדול kohen gadol is כשר. kasher. וחד
אמר, ve-chad amar, the other says guess it the opposite. פרו פסולה,
paro psulah, the cow of the כהן גדול kohen gadol is פסול,
pasul, פרה כשרה. parah kesherah. Okay. Now who says which? So let's
let's help out here and assign some names. תסתיים, tistayem, let's
conclude דרב הוא דאמר פרה פסולה, de-Rav hu de-amar parah psulah, that
רב Rav. is the one that says the פרה אדומה Para Aduma
is פסול pasul by a זר. zar. And we'd say that by
יום כיפור, Yom Kippur? somewhat unexpectedly, yes, it's not an עבודה avodah
and it could be done by a non-כהן. kohen. דאמר רבי זירא
de-amar Rabbi Zeira because רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira says: שחיטת פרה בזר
פסולה, shechitat parah be-zar psulah, that the shechting of the פרה אדומה
Para Aduma, by a non-כהן kohen is פסול. pasul. So that's exactly
that position. How do we know that's רב's Rav position? דאמר רבא
עלה, de-amar Rava alah, and רבא commented on it: אלעזר וחוקה שנינו
בה. Elazar ve-chukah shaninu bah. You know why the shechting of the
פרה אדומה Para Aduma? is פסול pasul by a non-כהן? kohen? Because
the complete in the פרה אדומה Para Aduma. in חוקת Chukat where
it talks about the פרה אדומה, Para Aduma it's constantly saying אלעזר
הכהן, Elazar ha-kohen, אלעזר הכהן, Elazar ha-kohen, אלעזר הכהן. Elazar ha-kohen. But
then it also says, how does the פרשה parsha open? זאת חוקת
התורה. zot chukat ha-Torah. So remember I told you before that the
way you know whether something is מעכב me'akev in these types of,
you know, is absolutely necessary in these types of things is either
because it's repeated or because of the word חוק. chok. So he
says the combination of the word חוק chok plus אלעזר Elazar equals
you need a כהן. kohen. Okay. So since רב Rav is explaining
this and seems to be affirming it, he seems to be affirming
it. So רב Rav is the one that says that פרה אדומה
Para Aduma needs a כהן kohen because of the language of חוק
chok and the emphasis of אלעזר. Elazar, Okay. Now we're going to
ask, but what about the one on on יום כיפור? Yom Kippur,
ורב, ve-Rav, now according to רב... Rav ורב, v'Rav, now according to
רב, Rav מאי שנא פרה Mai shna para? דכתיב d'chsiv אלעזר וחוקה?
Elazar v'chuka? By the פרה אדומה, Para Aduma it says אלעזר Elazar
and the language of חק, chok, זאת חקת התורה, zot chukat hatorah,
פרה. Para, Now by his פר on יום כיפור, Yom Kippur הא
כתיב אהרן וחוקה? ha k'siv Aharon v'chuka? So it's quite actually interesting
again, right,
the same way, you know, we sort of when it applies לדורות,
l'doros, it's not about personalities, but in the תורה, Torah פרה אדומה
parah adumah is all about אלעזר, Elazar and the יום כיפור Yom
Kippur. is all about אהרן. Aharon. בזאת יבא אהרן, bezot yavo Aharon,
אהרן, אהרן, אהרן. Aharon, Aharon, Aharon.
But it's the same logic, אהרן Aharon plus the language of חק,
chok, right, what's the language? והיתה זאת לכם לחקת עולם, v'hay'ta zot
lachem l'chukat olam, it says at the end of the עבודה avodah
of יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. So that combination should mean you need
a כהן. kohen. Okay, so and not only that, you need כהן
גדול, kohen gadol, right, like we normally say you need כהן גדול
kohen gadol by everything by יום כיפור. Yom Kippur, So the גמרא
Gemara says no, שחיטה לאו עבודה היא. shechitah lav avodah hi. No,
yes you need a כהן גדול kohen gadol for everything by things
that are the עבודה, avodah, but שחיטה shechitah is not an עבודה.
avodah. The same way
we had that debate about the drawing of the lots. Okay, whether
that was, whether that was, I'm not the debate, that was, that
was we said, the drawing of the lots is not an עבודה
avodah and in theory could be done even by a non-כהן גדול.
kohen gadol. So why is שחיטה shechitah not an עבודה? avodah? So
this actually תוספות Tosafot brings down two interesting explanations. רש"י Rashi explanation
is,
well, more like the proof that it's not an עבודה avodah is
that we know that שחיטה shechitah can normally be done by a
non-כהן. kohen. And anything, it's not so circular, I mean תוספות Tosafot
also a little bit argues circular, but it's not so circular, meaning
we work with the assumption, it's evidence, it's not definitional but it's
evidence. Meaning we work with the assumption that anything that can be
done, that anything that's an עבודה avodah must be done by a
כהן. kohen. So if we find something that as a general rule,
meaning forget יום כיפור, Yom Kippur as a general rule we know
elsewhere that קרבנות, because remember we did that whole thing on the
board where it says ושחט v'shachat and then it says בני אהרן,
בני אהרן, בני אהרן b'nei Aharon, b'nei Aharon, b'nei Aharon by the
whole opening פרשה parsha ויקרא, Vayikra, the כהנים kohanim are only introduced
after the שחיטה. shechitah.
So the fact that you don't need כהנים kohanim as a general
rule for שחיטה shechitah is evidence that it's not an עבודה. avodah.
An עבודה avodah would require כהנים. kohanim. And once it's not an
עבודה, avodah, then even on יום כיפור Yom Kippur it doesn't have
to be the כהן גדול, kohen gadol, the same way the drawing
of the lots doesn't have to be the כהן גדול. kohen gadol.
That's how רש"י Rashi's explains why שחיטה shechitah is not an עבודה.
avodah. תוספות Tosafot has another interesting explanation that I think you'll appreciate.
תוספות Tosafot quotes or has an explanation that it's not an עבודה
avodah
because it is a something that is required even outside of the
בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. Meaning, so it's not a בית המקדש Beis
HaMikdash ritual. שחיטה, shechitah, like מליקה melikah would be an עבודה avodah
and מליקה melikah requires a כהן, kohen, right, the with the bird,
with the neck. That's a unique בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash ritual. But
שחיטה shechitah we do by any animal that we want whether we
want to eat it, you want to bring it as a קרבן,
korban. whatever you want to do to it, שחיטה, shechitah, right, by
the עגלה ערופה, eglah arufah, breaking up of the, well that's non-עבודה
avodah that's out of the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. So the sort
of the universal aspect of שחיטה shechitah defines it as even when
it takes place in the מקדש, Mikdash, it's not an עבודה. avodah.
What's an עבודה? avodah? Catching the blood, moving the blood, throwing the
blood, all of those are unique to the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash.
So okay, so that's the question. Once, once you're saying that that
the שחיטה shechitah in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash on יום כיפור
Yom Kippur, can be done by a non-כהן, kohen, so why by
the פרה אדומה parah adumah don't you say the same thing? So
we'll talk about that's where we're going, yes.
So by that argument, in the מדבר, midbar, שחיטה shechitah would have
had
to been done by a כהן. kohen. Yeah, I don't think so.
Because I think, whatever.
But they didn't do
שחיטה, shechitah, but that was just at that time period. It doesn't
speak about its basic function. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like
this, it
asks now Michael's question, אי הכי פרה נמי. ei hachi parah nami.
If that's true that yes, everything requires a כהן גדול kohen gadol
by יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, everything requires a כהן kohen by פרה
אדומה, Parah Adumah but we're going to exclude שחיטה shechitah which isn't
an עבודה, avodah, so exclude it by the פרה Para as well.
No, שאני פרה דקדשי בדק הבית היא. shani parah d'kadshi bedek habayit
hi. פרה
אדומה Parah Adumah, is different. פרה אדומה Parah Adumah, is not really
a קרבן. korban. It's sanctified, but it's sanctified like
you would sanctify a beam of wood. It's sanctified for use in
the מקדש, Mikdash but not as an intrinsic קדושה kedusha to be
used as to be a קרבן. korban. Meaning it's sanctified but it's
a non-קרבן. korban But then, but therefore what? So the גמרא Gemara
says ולאו כל שכן הוא, v'lav kol shechein hu, is it not
like a קל וחומר, kal vachomer, כל שכן? kol shechein? If a
קרבן korban. can be done, isn't an עבודה avodah and doesn't need
a כהן, kohen, doesn't need כהן גדול, kohen gadol, so certainly something
that isn't even a קרבן. korban, So the גמרא Gemara. says, אמר
רב ששת בריה דרב אידי, Amar Rav Sheshet b'rei d'Rav Idi,
מידי דהוה אמראות נגעים. midi d'hava amara'os negaim. No, it's think about
the idea of looking at a נגע, nega, a spot of צרעת.
tzara'as. דלאו עבודה היא, d'lav avodah hi, that's not an עבודה, avodah,
right, the כהן kohen goes and he inspects the guy wherever he
is, it's not an עבודה. avodah. ובעיא כהונה, u'ba'ya kehuna, but you
still need a כהן. kohen. So what he's saying is like this,
it's a very interesting point. He's saying there are some things that
require a כהן, kohen, meaning it's, you know, what is this, it's
like we use this one of the things about prepositional logic. Just
because, to use רש"י's Rashi's argument, just because everything that is an
עבודה avodah So what he's saying is like this. It's a very
interesting point. He's saying there are some things that require a כהן,
kohen, meaning it's, you know, what is this, it's like this is
one of the things about prepositional logic. Just because, to use רש''י's
Rashi argument, just because everything that is an עבודה avoda requires a
כהן, kohen, doesn't mean that everything that requires a כהן kohen is
an עבודה. avoda. So he says, it be the fact that it's
done out of the מקדש Mikdash means it's not an עבודה. avoda.
That's a whole process in itself and it's not an עבודה. avoda.
And we have things that the whole thing isn't an עבודה avoda
and requires a כהן kohen like מראות נגעים. mar'os nega'im. So once
the תורה'ס Torah's telling me that this non-עבודה avoda requires a כהן,
kohen, I'm not going to say שחיטה shechita
is any different than any other part of the process. The whole
thing isn't an עבודה avoda and it requires a כהן. kohen. So
in the מקדש Mikdash, where the focus is עבודה, avoda, and if
you need a כהן kohen or a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol on
יום כיפור, Yom Kippur then it's only for the עבודה avoda part,
and שחיטה shechita could be even with a זר, zar, let alone
a non-כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. But outside of the מקדש, it's not
about עבודה avoda at all. So if you're going to require a
כהן kohen for part of it, you're going to require a כהן
kohen for all of it.
And wouldn't we say they both need a כהן?
kohen? Why can't anyone say... you could in theory. You could say
that neither do. Okay, but this is the position. Now, that's רב.
Rav That's why רב Rav? says no by the כהן גדול, Kohen
Gadol, yes by the פרה אדומה. Parah Adumah Okay. ושמואל דאמר פרה
פסולה, U'Shmuel d'amar Para pesula,
now we're going to deal with שמואל. Shmuel. שמואל Shmuel says the
opposite. כהן גדול Kohen Gadol requires,
on יום כיפור Yom Kippur he needs a כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol,
a זר zar is invalid, but the פרה אדומה Parah Adumah does
not. מאי שנא mai shna פרה? parah So we get why on
יום כיפור Yom Kippur. it needs to be a... it actually needs
to be the כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. דכתיב אהרן וחוקה, De'ksiv Aharon
v'chuka, like we've been saying.
It says אהרן Aharon or כהן kohen and it says חוק, chok,
and therefore you need
a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol for everything, even for the שחיטה. shechita.
פרה נמי הכתיב אלעזר וחוקה. Para nami haksiv Elazar v'chuka.
So by the פרה אדומה, Parah Adumah it speaks about אלעזר הכהן
Elazar ha'kohen and says חוקת התורה. chukas ha'Torah.
So again, I get why you need it on יום כיפור. Yom
Kippur Why don't you need it by the פרה אדומה? Parah Adumah?
So the גמרא Gemara says: שאני התם דכתיב ושחט אותה לפניו. Shani
hasam de'ksiv v'shachat osah le'fanav.
Right?
The same way, it's quite fascinating. The same way we know that
שחיטה בזר shechita be'zar is כשר, kasher, if you read the פסוקים
psukim closely. Remember those opening פסוקים psukim of ויקרא? Vayikra? It says
you bring your קרבן, korban, you שחט shecht it, and then the
בני אהרן Bnei Aharon catch the blood and take the blood. So
it's very clearly the תורה'ס Torah's really saying the שחיטה shechita is
done by the owner of the קרבן, by a non-כהן. kohen. So
what he's saying is, if you read the תורה Torah. closely, it's
saying the same thing by the פרה אדומה. parah adumah. It says
it will be slaughtered in אלעזר'ס Elazar's presence, somebody will שחט shecht
it לפניו. le'fanav. So anybody, generic, anybody can שחט shecht it in
his presence. It doesn't have to be a כהן. kohen. That's why,
okay, שהא
זר שוחט ואלעזר רואה. she'hei zar shochet v'Elazar ro'eh. A non-כהן kohen
can שחט shecht and אלעזר Elazar could be seeing. So the פסוקים
psukim make it clear that that could be done by a non-כהן.
kohen. ורב, v'Rav,
now how would רב Rav explain the אותה לפניו? otah le'fanav? שלא
יסיח דעתו ממנה. she'lo yasi'ach da'ato mimena.
It doesn't mean another person is שחיטה shechting it in his presence.
It means he, אלעזר Elazar or the כהן, kohen, שחט shechts it
in his presence. Now, how do you שחט shecht something not in
your presence? So he's שחיטה shechting it in your presence means in
your existential presence, that you have to be paying attention and you
have to be, you know, you have to be present. Is everybody
here, is everybody present here, you know. So post-modern. Exactly.
So that's what it means. אלעזר Elazar שחט shechts it, but he
has to be present, you know,
psychologically present. Okay. So that's what it means. ושמואל שלא יסיח דעתו
מנליה? U'Shmuel she'lo yasi'ach da'ato minalei? And for now the גמרא'ס Gemara's
assuming that everybody holds of this criteria, so where does שמואל Shmuel
know that the כהן kohen cannot distract himself since it says somebody
else is שחיטה shechting it? So נפקא ליה ושרף את הפרה לעיניו.
nafka lei mi'v'saraf es ha'para le'einav. It burned it to his eyes.
So again, means in his, you know, he is supervising, in his
presence, so he has to be he has to be paying attention.
ורב, v'Rav, what would רב say? חד בשחיטה וחד בשריפה. chad bi'shechita
v'chad bi'sreifa. No, the תורה Torah, has to tell you twice. That
at the שחיטה shechita you have to be, it's all done by
the כהן, kohen, but it has to emphasize both at the שחיטה
shechita and at the שריפה sreifa that you have to be
fully present and not be distracted. צריכא. Tzricha. דאי כתב רחמנא בשחיטה,
De'i kasav Rachmana bi'shechita, he had,
you need to tell me both places. If it just said by
the שחיטה shechita you have to, you can't be distracted, משום דתחלת
עבודה, mishum de'techilas avoda, that's the most important. That's the beginning of
the process. So, you know, that gives identity to the whole process.
So there you really can't be distracted. אבל שריפה, Aval sreifa, but
once the whole thing is going on, you know, is on the
right track, אימא לא, eima lo, maybe you don't have to be
fully present at the time of שריפה. sreifa. You can be distracted.
צריכא. Tzricha. So it had to tell me even there you need
it. ודאי כתב רחמנא בשריפה, V'de'i kasav Rachmana bi'sreifa, had it said
you need it just at the burning, משום דהשתא הוא דמכשרה פרה.
mishum de'hashta hu de'miskashra para.
Maybe that's the most important time because that is when it becomes
ashes. That's when the thing actually becomes, you know, the end result
of what it's supposed to be. אבל שחיטה, Aval shechita, but the
שחיטה shechita which is only what we would call like a הכשר
מצוה, hechsher mitzvah, get, you know, part of the process, אימא לא,
eima lo, maybe you don't have to be paying so close attention.
צריכא. Tzricha. It needs to tell you both. Okay. So you could
say you should always pay attention. I know, but the question is,
is being distracted invalid?
Oh, yeah, you should always pay attention.
Oh, that was a good one. Okay. Listen. You should always pay
attention. I said, "What did you say?" Okay, I missed that. You
know, part of the process, אימא לא *eima lo*, maybe you don't
have to be paying it so much close attention. צריכא *tsricha*, needs
to tell you both. Okay. So you're saying we should always pay
attention? I know, but the גזלן *gazlan* is being distracted invalidly. You
should always be paying attention. That was a good one. Okay. You
should always pay attention. I said what did you say?
Okay,
I missed that also. I would have, you should have said what
you said, I wasn't paying attention. Okay, anyway, חברא ש״ס *chavra shas*.
Okay.
So I just want to take a moment to stop and tell
us where we are, remind us where we are. So you know,
as Michael pointed out, in view you could have four possibilities. You
could argue פרה אדומה parah adumah *Para Adumah*, you could argue the
פר *par* of יום כיפור Yom Kippur. *Yom Kippur*. Interestingly, you know,
there's like both positions say that פרה *Para* is that one, that
they're different, that the פרה אדומה parah adumah. *Para Adumah* is different
than פרות *parot*, but they come out the different ways. So what's
the argument? So again to remind us, by יום כיפור Yom Kippur
*Yom Kippur*, both places it speaks either of אהרן Aharon *Aharon* and
says חוק chok *chok* or אלעזר Elazar. *Elazar* and says חוק chok
*chok* and in general we assume that the פר יום כיפור Yom
Kippur *par Yom Kippur* requires not just a כהן Kohen. *kohen* but
a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol, *Kohen Gadol* and we assume that the
פרה אדומה parah adumah *Para Adumah* requires a כהן Kohen. *kohen*, so
we know that basically it must be a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol
*Kohen Gadol*, must be a כהן kohen. *kohen*. What would be the
argument to exclude שחיטה shchitah *shechita*? So by יום כיפור *Yom Kippur*
the argument is that it's not an עבודה avodah *avodah*, either because
elsewhere it's כשר kosher, בזר *kosher bezar* or because it occurs outside
the בית המקדש *Beit Hamikdash*. It's not an עבודה *avodah*, so that's
excluded. Now the other position that says I don't care is interesting
to think about. Does he
say שחיטה shchitah *shechita* is an עבודה *avodah*? Does he say things
that aren't an עבודה *avodah* require a כהן kohen. *kohen*? Would he
say the drawing of the lots you can't have the סגן sgan
*sgan* involved? How does the כהן kohen? *kohen* use his left hand?
What's the difference between the drawing of the lots and the שחיטה
shchitah *shechting*? Now obviously for us here it feels like there's a
huge difference, and it raises an interesting question of could you say
שחיטה shchitah *shechita* is an עבודה *avodah* even though it's כשר kasher
בזר *kosher bezar*? Right? Why would somebody say the שחיטה shchitah, *shechita*
requires a כהן גדול kohen gadol. *Kohen Gadol* yet you know, but
say other things, let's say the drawing
of the lots, you know, does not? So that's something to think
about. But that's the issue about whether the, about why to exclude
the שחיטה shchitah *shechita*. And when you come to the פרה אדומה
*Para Adumah*, that's not about being an עבודה *avodah* as the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says, that's outside the בית המקדש *Beit Hamikdash*. So why
would you exclude the שחיטה shchitah *shechita*? So here the only reason
so far is not really a conceptual one but based on the
פסוק posuk *pasuk*. ושחט אתו לפניו *veshachat oto lefanav*, which says a
close reading will show you that it's not אלעזר Elazar *Elazar* doing
the שחיטה *shechita*. And then it really does in a way it
does resonate with this idea of שחיטה לאו עבודה *shechita lav avodah*
because as I said if you point a, you know, close reading
of the פסוקים psukim *psukim* make it clear that whether bringing the
קרבן *korban*, whether the פרה אדומה *Para Adumah*, somebody else is doing
the שחיטה *shechita*. And that's the point that the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
is making.
Does it mean that you can't?
He's saying it's חוקה *chuka*, it has to be exactly? No because
it says anyone, anyone, you know, anyone presumably even himself. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this: למיעוטי מאי *lemutei mai*?
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* assumes, תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot* says wasn't exactly
sure why the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* assumes it, but the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* assumes that we've mentioned this idea of you can't be distracted
by the שחיטה *shechita* and the שריפה *sreifa*, somehow it suggests that
there are other times where
you're allowed to be distracted. So what are we excluding from this
requirement of not being distracted? אילימא למיעוטי אסיפת אפרה ומילוי מים *ileima
lemutei asifat afara umiluy mayim*,
maybe the other, you know, there are other, a lot of other
parts of the process. So maybe the gathering of the ashes and
the filling of the water וקידוש *vekidush*
for the sake of then putting the ashes in. So maybe that
doesn't require, you know, that would be כשר *kosher* even if you
were distracted. No, למשמרת למי נדה כתיב *lemishmeret lemei nida ktiv*, the
verse says to-for an observance for the waters of נדה *nida*, I
mean like sprinkling. In general the word נדה *nida* is probably close
questions what it means, but most you know there's a pretty large
consensus based on the other parallels that it's like the word of
זבה *zavah* and it means a flow. So it talks about a
woman who has her flow, but it talks about ashes that are
sprinkled or water that is sprinkled is the waters of sprinkling, מי
נדה *mei nida* because you know it's a, it's not a flowing
as a flow but it's still the movement of liquid. So למשמרת
למי נדה כתיב *lemishmeret lemei nida ktiv*. So it says that so
for a משמרת *mishmeret*. So this process at the end of the
gathering of the ashes and of the water, all of that you
need to be watching. That's what the word משמרת *mishmeret* means. אלא
למיעוטי השלכת עץ ארז ואזוב ושני תולעת *ela lemutei hashlechat etz erez
ve'ezov ushni tolaat*, we're getting back to that. Here's the one thing
you wouldn't, it would be excluded from the need of a כהן
kohen, *kohen*, that the throwing of the stuff into, not the need
of a כהן kohen. *kohen*, the need of paying attention. The requirement
not to be distracted would be the throwing of the stuff into
the fire. Not of the פרה *para* in the fire but of
the other stuff, the wood and and the red string etc. דלאו
גופא דפרה נינהו *delav gufah depara ninhu*. Since it's not something done
on the פרה אדומה *Para Adumah* itself, everything else is done with
the פרה *para*, שחיטה *shechting* it with the blood, with the burning
it, its ashes, all that stuff is about the פרה אדומה *Para
Adumah* itself, that all requires this paying attention. But this thing which
obviously is necessary, you could be if you were distracted and it
could still be כשר *kosher*.
What, yeah where would we see that?
Right. Yeah that's what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is saying. Okay, so
that was just something that would be excluded from this requirement to
pay attention. Now איתמר *itmar*.
But also sprinkling, right, does that-?
Yeah no that totally needs.
So here's the one action that the תלמוד *Talmud* allows us to
be mindless about.
Yeah you know I would say בדיעבד *bedieved* but okay. איתמר *itmar*.
Okay it was taught. שחיטת פרה בזר *shechitat para bezar*, back to
that. Okay another another version of this debate. The שחיטה *shechting* of
the פרה אדומה *Para Adumah* with a non-כהן kohen. *kohen*. רב אמי
אמר כשר רב יצחק נפחא אמר פסולה *Rav Ami amar kosher Rav
Yitzchak Napcha amar psula*. רב אמי *Rav Ami* says כשר *kosher*, רב
יצחק *Rav Yitzchak* bar- נפחא says it's פסול, posul, so similar to
the debate of רב and שמואל. Shmuel. עולא אמר כשירה, Ula amar
keshera, now עולא Ula said it was כשר, ואמרי לה פסולה. v'amri
lah pesula. Some remember עולא Ula having said that it was פסול.
posul. Okay, so it's just lining up the different opinions of where,
you know, there's a long-standing debate here, who says what? Okay, now,
מתיב רב יהושע בר אבא לסיועיה לרב. Masiv Rav Yehoshua bar Abba
l'siyu'ei l'Rav. So רב יהושע בר אבא Rav Yehoshua bar Abba brought
the following challenge to שמואל'ס Shmuel's position and to support רב to
show that everybody remember what רב said?
Which one was רב? רב said that פרה אדומה is פסול בזר.
pasul b'zar. Okay, right, he was the one that said שחיטה לאו
עבודה היא shechita lav avoda hi that a כהן גדול, kohen gadol,
you don't need a כהן גדול kohen gadol, on יום כיפור for
it, but it's פסול, pasul, but פרה, you need a כהן. kohen.
So he's going to try to prove that פרה does need a
כהן. kohen. Let's take a look. אין לי אלא הזאת מימיה, Ein
li ella hazas meimeha, so this is a ברייתא. beraisa. אין לי
אלא הזאת מימיה שאין כשירה באשה כבאיש ואין כשירה אלא ביום. Ein
li ella hazas meimeha she'ein keshera b'isha k'be'ish v'ein keshera ella bayom.
So the point of this ברייתא braita is to determine which parts
of the process of פרה אדומה must be done during the day.
Okay, let me tell you the basic structure of the ברייתא. We're
going to start with an assumption that a certain thing, the הזאה,
haza'ah, okay, the sprinkling itself, must be done during the day. And
from the fact that the sprinkling must be done during the day,
we're going to, we'll worry about why later, but that's our foundation
assumption, that when you're done and you sprinkle the water on somebody,
that has to be in the day. Once that's true, we're going
to say, can we therefore make a קל וחומר, kal v'chomer, somehow
make a derivation and say if that has to be done in
the day, other parts of the process have to be done in
the day as well? And here's how we're going to make it,
make that argument. This sprinkling can, so here let's take a look,
let's read this, hold on, where were we? Okay,
אין לי אלא הזאת מימיה. ein li ella hazas meimeha. So the
sprinkling of the water, אין כשירה באשה כבאיש, ein keshera b'isha k'be'ish,
cannot be done by a woman, we'll see why later, where they
learn it out from. A lot of the part of this פרה
אדומה says איש טהור, ish tahor, איש טהור, ish tahor, etc., and
the גמרא understands that means man. ואין כשירה אלא ביום, v'ein keshera
ella bayom, and it has to be day. So that we know
by the sprinkling. מניין לרבות שחיטתה וקבלת
דמה והזאת דמה ושריפתה והשלכת עץ ארז ואזוב ושני תולעת? Minayin l'rabos
shechitasa v'kabbalas dama v'hazas dama v'sreifasa v'hashlachas etz erez v'eizov u'shni
tola'as? How do I know all the other parts of the process,
shechting, getting the blood, sprinkling the blood, burning it, throwing in the
stuff in the fire? How do I know all of that also
can only be in the day? תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, תורה. Torah
So it says תורה, Torah it says זאת חוקת התורה. zos chukas
haTorah. So תורה Torah means it's inclusive. Sometimes often תורה Torah inclusive
means we're more flexible, but here it means we're including everything in
the same category. And if it's all in the same category, if
one thing needs to be day, everything needs to be day. יכול
שאני מרבה אף אסיפת אפרה ומילוי מים וקידוש? Yachol shani marbeh af
asifas afra u'miluy mayim v'kidush?
Maybe I'll also demand for the daytime criteria for after it becomes
ashes, gathering the ashes, filling the water, קידוש kidush is putting the
ashes in the water, so maybe even that has to be in
the day? תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, זאת. zos. It says זאת חוקת
התורה. zos chukas haTorah. Some things, זאת zot is a limiting word,
so some things aren't in the category. So now the obvious question
is going to be what's in the category and what's out of
the category?
So you're saying that תורה Torah is saying just like the other
things need attention, so too the שח... shach...
so that's the question, why here we exclude certain things from the
criteria and before we included other things? Yeah, so תוספות asks the
question, okay, more or less. Okay, so מה ראית לרבות את אלו
ולהוציא את אלו? mah ra'isa l'rabos es elu u'l'hotzi es elu? What
criteria did you use? Right, you have a word that's inclusive, a
word that's exclusive. Which criteria do you use to say that they
all have to be the same and which things don't have to
be the same? אחר שריבה הכתוב ומיעט, Achar she'riba hakasuv u'mi'et, so
after the פסוק pasuk was sort of inclusive, then it
limited. אמרת, Amarta, הרי אנו למדין כולם מהזאת מימיה. harey anu l'meidin
kulam mehazas meimeha. Here's why we're going to put the things we
put in the same category as the sprinkling but exclude the ashes
part of it. So why? כולם kulam we learn out everything we
said, all the other parts of the process from the sprinkling. מה
הזאת מימיה אין כשירה באשה כבאיש, mah hazas meimeha ein keshera b'isha
k'be'ish, like we said, it has to be a man, ואין כשירה
אלא ביום, v'ein keshera ella bayom, and it requires day. We know
those two criteria. אף אני ארבה שחיטתה וקבלת דמה והזאת דמה ושריפתה
והשלכת עץ ארז ואזוב ושני תולעת. Af ani arbeh shechitasa v'kabbalas dama
v'hazas dama v'sreifasa v'hashlachas etz erez v'eizov u'shni tola'as.
I'll also then include all the other parts of the process I
mentioned, shechting, capturing the blood, sprinkling the blood, burning it, throwing the
stuff in the fire, all of those I'm going to say are
the same and require daytime. Why? And here finally is the key
argument. הואיל ואין כשירה באשה כבאיש אין כשירה אלא ביום. Ho'il v'ein
keshera b'isha k'be'ish ein keshera ella bayom.
Because they have, we know one of the criteria already is similar.
Okay, so again, the assumption we're working with is that the sprinkling
we know has to be a man, it has to be daytime,
and for all the other parts of the process we don't know
daytime, but we do know the requirement of man. So since it's
already similar in that type of a higher, you know, of a
higher requirement in the sense of like a narrower criterion, so we're
going to say if it has that type of a similar criteria,
it will also have the criterion of daytime as opposed to... also
the gathering of the ashes and the water and the putting the
ashes in the water, which can be done even by a woman,
and therefore can also be done at nighttime. It doesn't have those
additional criteria. So that tells, determines what I include in the grouping
and exclude if I know they share one criteria, I'll assume they
share the other as opposed to these which do not have that
criteria.
It's an assumption.
Got it, three out of four criteria, so you assume the last
one.
Well, yeah, but it was really one out of two, but okay,
right. Okay, ומוציאני u-motziani
so I will say those אין שהם אלא ביום. ein she-heim ela
be-yom. So all those part of the process since we know they
have to be a man, we'll assume they also have to be
in the daytime. ומוציאני אסיפת אפרה ומילוי מים וקידוש u-motziani asifat afarah
u-milui mayim ve-kidush
but what I will exclude from the requirement of daytime, what I
will exclude from the requirement of daytime is the gathering of the
ashes, the filling of the water and the putting the ashes in
the water, why? הואיל וכשרים באישה כבאיש ho'il ve-kshairim be-ishah ke-ve-ish because
since I know again elsewhere, we don't know how we know any
of this stuff, but since I know elsewhere that that can be
done by a man and a woman, or a woman, כשרים נמי
ביום ובלילה. kshairim nami be-yom u-va-lailah. It can also be done at
day or at night. Okay, so the מילוי מים
milui mayim is the what?
Filling the water into the vessel. And then the gathering of the
ashes, you put the water in the vessel, then you put the
ashes in the water. Okay, and the קידוש is the putting the
ashes in the water. Okay, so so this now so so this
is the argument that again, the argument is most of the process
except for the stuff with the ashes at the very end of
making the water into the water, that you know, that doesn't have
to be at the day, but all the other stuff is argued
to the day, why? Because we know elsewhere and now we're going
to figure out where is that elsewhere, that that has already an
additional criteria that it has to be a man. So we'll assume
it has the other additional criteria of day just like those two
criteria are found by the sprinkling of the water as opposed to
the stuff with the ashes and the making and putting the ashes
in the water, that doesn't have the first criteria, it doesn't have
the second. Now before we go on to see how this supports
the argument that it has to פסול בזר, pasul be-zar, the basic
argument will be the reason a woman is being excluded from all
of this is that not that she's a woman, but that she's
not a כהן. kohen, That it's really not the excluding of a
woman, it's really פסול בזר psul be-zar and that's going to be
the support of the idea that פרה אדומה is פסול בזר, pasul
be-zar, that the שחיטה is פסול בזר. pasul be-zar. But before we
do that I just want you to look at one רש"י Rashi
which you know because again what's clear about this is that the
פסוקים psukim only got us so far. They said some things are
in the category, some are out, and and the גמרא said so
let's figure out how to group them. So if you look at
the רש"י Rashi that starts with שרבה הכתוב ומיעט shereibah ha-katuv u-mi'at
about ten lines down in the narrow lines, רש"י says ולא פירש
מה ריבה ומה מיעט ve-lo peiraish mah ribah u-mah mi'at and the
Torah wasn't clear clear what's in the category what's out of the
category. ומעתה לא מסרן אלא להתבונן בה את האמת ואת הישר. u-mei'atah
lo masran ela le-hitbonen bah et ha-emet ve-et ha-yashar. I just like
that language. Now you see the Torah has only given them over,
you know, to the to the Rabbis to sort of you know
pick like look into it, you know, and find out what is
the true, what is the right. It's funny the word ישר yashar
in this context, maybe it means right thinking, but use your rational
logic you know and judgment to figure out how to group it.
How to how to categorize it.
The opposite of דעת תורה.
da'at Torah. Exactly. So anyway, so let's take a look back in
the גמרא. So now we're going to see the argument. This is
all brought in to prove that שחיטה is has to be פסול
בזר, pasul be-zar, has to be a כהן. kohen? So the גמרא
says like this: והא מאי תיובתא. ve-ha mai tiyuvta. Why was that
a challenge to the one that says שחיטה can be done by
a non-כהן? kohen אילימא מדפסלינן באישה פסלינן נמי בזר eileima mid-paslinan be-ishah
paslinan nami be-zar which is what it seems the argument was. If
you say that the reason that from the by the same virtue
that we're invalidating a woman, we're invalidating a non-כהן, kohen. meaning it's
not about a woman, how do we know a woman's not good
for this? It's really about her not being a כהן. kohen, That's
your assumption and therefore it proves that שחיטה needs a כהן. kohen.
No. הזיה תוכיח. haza'ah tochi'ach. I'll show you that that's not always
true. The sprinkling of the actual water of the פרה אדומה it
will prove otherwise. שפסולה באישה she-psulah be-ishah we're going that remember was
the paradigm the one we started from. And that we are again
all of this we know elsewhere, that the sprinkling of the water
cannot be done by a woman, וכשרה בזר u-kshairah be-zar does not
require a כהן. kohen. So the whole the whole גמרא was using
that as the paradigm. The same way this has to be day
and man, the rest has to be day and man. But גמרא
says the sprinkling having to be man is not about having to
be כהן. kohen. That can be done by a non-כהן, kohen, but
we're going to see that it's going to require man so maybe
the same assumption is about the other parts of the process, maybe
the שחיטה, maybe not all the other parts, but maybe at least
the שחיטה can be has to be a man but doesn't have
to be a כהן? kohen. So the גמרא says no. אמר אביי
היינו תיובתיה. amar Abaye hainu tiyuvteih. This is why it was a
question. אישה מאי טעמא ishah mai ta'ama because where do you know
what's the basis of excluding woman? We'll find out later why we
know that the sprinkling of the water can be done by a
non-כהן kohen. but only by a man. But we have פסוקים pesukim
that that's the basis of. But how about the other parts of
the process? The שחיטה and the burning. burning and the blood. How
do we know there? What would be the basis there to exclude
a woman? The only basis to exclude a woman in that part
of the process is because of the need for a כהן. kohen
So, so, where is it? היינו דקא מסייע אשה מאי טעמא. Hainu
deka masaye isha mai ta'ama. What would be the only basis for
excluding a woman in the earlier parts of the process? Because אלעזר
ולא אשה Elazar velo isha requires אלעזר Elazar. and not a woman.
So זר נמי. zar nami. So the point is that, so the
only basis for excluding the woman would be the same basis for
excluding a כהן, kohen a non-כהן. kohen. אלעזר אלעזר ולא זר. Elazar
Elazar velo zar. So אלעזר Elazar, and not and not a non-כהן.
kohen, So in the end, so that was a complicated proof but
in the end it boiled down to the fact that we start
with the assumption that the sprinkling of the water has to be
with a man and in the daytime and we're going to find
out but can be a non-כהן. kohen Okay. And the גמרא then
makes, learns out the whole idea, the ברייתא of daytime to most
other parts of the process except the part of ashes. Starting with
the assumption, and this is the point, that all those parts cannot
be done by a woman. So although the גמרא says you find
one aspect of פרה אדומה that has to be by a man
but doesn't require a כהן, kohen, by all that part of the
process the only basis in terms of the verse that you would
have to exclude woman is by insisting on אלעזר. Elazar. And on
that basis, if you're going to insist on אלעזר Elazar, and on
that basis exclude woman from that part of the process, then you
also have to exclude a non-כהן. And that is the proof that
it's כשר with a non-כהן. Let's start a little bit. So that's
the end of that discussion for now. Now we're going to talk
actually about just reading the פסוקים pesukim and just looking at the
different stages of the פרה אדומה, okay? So, so let's just get
a little bit started on this. Okay. So the גמרא says like
this. אמר עולא כל הפרשה כולה משמע מוציא מיד משמע ומשמע ממילא.
Amar Ulla kol haparsha kulla mashma motzi miyad mashma umashma mimela. So
the whole פרה פרשה parsha פרה אדומה, the implication of the verses
both imply sometimes when it is it is an exception מוציא מיד
משמע, motzi miyad mashma, excepting from the way it sounds like, and
ומשמע ממילא, umashma mimela, sometimes it sounds like exactly like it sounds
like. So what he's basically saying is we're going to go through
the פסוקים pesukim. and a lot of this has to do with
the question of do you require a כהן or not a כהן
and we're going to see that based on the way the rabbis
read it, sometimes things are read as an exception from the rule
and sometimes things are read naturally. I want to say one word
about the word משמע mashma in this context of of reading פסוקים.
pesukim, You know משמע mashma normally you could you just get in
the you know normal like non-פסוק pasuk related, just in normal discourse,
it sounds like that you're saying this, you know, it's משמע mashma
this, it implies this. What? A logical argument, right.
So but when it's
applied to פסוקים, pesukim, this is actually important that it's a word
like פשט pshat and it actually, you know, the simple sense of
the פסוק pasuk and in a way actually more what we mean
when we say פשט. pshat. We assume when we say פשט pshat
it means the simple sense of the verse. Of course, who defines
what simple means? So I think a good working explanation is what
that verse would have meant to the people at that time. Like
how they would have understood it, okay. That's what we assume the
word פשט pshat means. But actually the word פשט pshat according to
in in rabbinic literature means the the the sort of canonical, the
accepted rabbinic interpretation of the verse. Because when think about the line
that the גמרא says פשוטו כמשמעו, pshuto kemashmao, the פשט pshat of
this פסוק is what it sounds like. Of course the פשט pshat
is what it sounds like! So actually what that means is משמעו,
mashmao, the word משמע mashma means what it sounds like, the the
simple sense of the verse. The פשט pshat means the way the
rabbis read the verse. Okay. So it's actually an important difference that
the פשט pshat is the standardized interpretation, משמע mashma really means the
פשט pshat of the verse. So he is saying that when you
read these פסוקים, pesukim. some of the things are משמעו, mashmao, are
within the simple sense, and some are מוציא מיד משמעו, motzi miyad
mashmao, are divert from the simple sense. Let's just read one or
two פסוקים. Okay. ונתתם אתה אל אלעזר הכהן. Unasattem otah el Elazar
hakohen. You should give it the פרה אדומה to אלעזר. Elazar אותה
אלעזר ולא לדורות אלעזר. Otah Elazar velo ledorot Elazar. The פרה אדומה
for this generation has to be to אלעזר, Elazar. but in future
generations it doesn't require אלעזר. Elazar, Now what does that mean? איכא
דאמרי, Ika de'amri, some say לדורות בכהן גדול, ledorot bekohen gadol, we
go up in our criteria. That's new, we never heard of that
before. The פרה אדומה requires a כהן גדול. kohen gadol ואיכא דאמרי,
Ve'ika de'amri, and some say לדורות בכהן הדיוט, ledorot bekohen hedyot, that
in future generations it requires any כהן. Okay. But it doesn't require
a somebody that's like אלעזר, Elazar. because if it would require somebody
like אלעזר Elazar, you might say it needs somebody who's not the
כהן גדול, kohen gadol, not the top boss, but not your normal
כהן, some guy somebody in the middle, like a סגן or something.
No, לדורות ledorot it is not following the model of אלעזר. Elazar
So that would be מוציא מיד משמעו, motzi miyad mashmao, right? The
משמע mashma if I ask you what type of a כהן what
do you need future generation for for פרה אדומה? You would say
well the תורה is always talking about אלעזר, so probably somebody that's
a little bit close to being like a כהן גדול, kohen gadol,
right? That's probably what you would say. That would be משמע. mashma.
But no, it doesn't have to be like אלעזר. Now that could
go in two directions: כהן גדול kohen gadol. or כהן הדיוט. kohen
hedyot. So let's just see the reasons, and that's what we'll end
with today. בשלמא למאן דאמר לדורות בכהן הדיוט, Bishlama leman de-amar ledoros
be-kohen hedyot, if you say future generations like we've been assuming is
a normal כהן, that's good, שפיר, shapir, that makes sense. אלא למאן
דאמר לדורות בכהן גדול, Ella leman de-amar ledoros be-kohen gadol, but if
future generations require כהן גדול, kohen gadol מנא ליה? mena leh? Where
do you get it from? גמר חוקה חוקה מיום הכיפורים. Gamar chukka
chukka mi-Yom ha-Kippurim. It says from what we've been talking about. It
says חוק by פרה אדומה. It says חוק by יום כיפור. If
יום כיפור requires a כהן גדול, kohen gadol, פרה אדומה requires a
כהן גדול. And I think that's quite fascinating and we'll end with
this, because you know these two עבודות avodos that the תורה spends
like a lot of time talking about the process and are very
much like communal concerns and these, you know, very like weighty rituals
is the עבודה of יום כיפור and the פרה אדומה. And both
of them have personalities assigned to it, אהרן Aharon and אלעזר, right?
And the question is how does that translate לדורות? ledoros? So what
this position is saying is actually לדורות ledoros the אלעזר position translates
just like the אהרן position into the meaning of כהן גדול for
both. Okay, but our assumption has been not that way. Our assumption
is that's a כהן גדול, the other one, the פרה אדומה becomes
a כהן הדיוט. kohen hedyot.
All righty,
phenomenal.